<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Plain English: or, The sectaries anatomized. Wherein the honor of the three estates of the kingdom is maintained, the government both of church and common-wealth is pleaded for: and this famous City of London, and their faithfull Remonstrance is vindicated from such false aspersions as lately have been cast upon it. Imprimatur. James Cranford.</title>
            <author>Jones, Captain.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 63 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 15 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A87635</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99861624</idno>
  <idno type="VID">113763</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2240961621</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing J961C</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E350_11</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R201046</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99861624</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-99861624e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A87635)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 113763)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 57:E350[11])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Plain English: or, The sectaries anatomized. Wherein the honor of the three estates of the kingdom is maintained, the government both of church and common-wealth is pleaded for: and this famous City of London, and their faithfull Remonstrance is vindicated from such false aspersions as lately have been cast upon it. Imprimatur. James Cranford.</title>
                  <author>Jones, Captain.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 26 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by T.R. and E.M. for Ralph Smith, at the signe of the Bible in Corn-hill neer the Royall-Exchange.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1646.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Attributed to Captain Jones by Wing.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "by Captaine Jones"; Aug" 17".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="corporate_name">Church of England --  Government --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term type="corporate_name">City of London (England). --  Court of Common Council --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term type="topical_term">Church polity --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term type="topical_term">Separatists --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-06 </date>
            <label>John Latta </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-06 </date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:113763:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:113763:1"/>
            <p>Plain English: OR, THE SECTARIES ANATOMIZED.</p>
            <p>Wherein the honor of the three Estates of the Kingdom is maintained, the government both of Church and Common-wealth is pleaded for:</p>
            <p>And this famous City of LONDON, and their faithfull REMONSTRANCE is Vindi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated from such false aspersions as late<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly have been cast upon it.</p>
            <q>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="license" subtype="imprimatur">
                        <p>
                           <hi>Imprimatur.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <closer>
                           <signed>JAMES CRANFORD.</signed>
                        </closer>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Isaiah 59. vers. 8, 9 13.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>The way of peace they know not, and there is no judgement in their going: they have made them crooked paths; whosoever goeth therein, shall not know peace.</p>
               <p>Therefore is judgement farre from us, neither doth justice overtake us: we wait for light, but behold obscurity; for brightnesse, but we walk in darknesse.</p>
               <p>In transgressing and lying against the Lord, and departing away from our God, speaking oppression and revolt, conceiving and uttering from the heart words of false<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>T. R.</hi> and <hi>E. M.</hi> for <hi>Ralph Smith,</hi> at the signe of the Bible in Corn-hill neer the Royall-Exchange. 1646.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="treatise">
            <pb facs="tcp:113763:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:113763:2"/>
            <head>Plain English: OR, THE SECTARIES ANATOMIZED.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>O speak the truth plainly, with intent do ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance Truth, and to depresse Error, is a duty which concerns us all, and were it now as ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally observed and practised by us of this City and Kingdom, as is the contrary, I might then have spared this paines, an turned sighs and sorrow into singing, and these complain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings into rejoycings: but finding Error with its Patrons and Abet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors in such request, and so much in fashion, <hi>Si natura negat, &amp;c.</hi> Give me leave to write unto them, to shame the deceivers, and admonish such who are in danger of being deceived by them. I shall therefore addresse my discourse to the unknown Authour of a Pamphlet called a <hi>Moderate Reply to the Cities Remon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strance,</hi> and through him to all the rest of his Associates, and by way of generall answer and recrimination together; but in the first place I appeale to every consciencious and wel-meaning man to judge whether that and other Pamphlets published in answer to the said <hi>Remonstrance,</hi> do not appeare to be most false scan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalous, yea, and destructive to the true interest of every English and religious subject, and desperatly wounding all good govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:113763:3"/>by incouraging and strengthning the hands of all the fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Champions of Sedition and confusion.</p>
            <p>Wherefore who ever you be that was the Authour of that Pamphlet (if you have not quiet lost that noble endowment of reason, the distinguishing character betwixt sober and mad men; betwixt men and beasts) consider what will be the issue of your labours if they accomplish their end; What good, nay what mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chief, what horrid ruines and distractions will they produce to this our native late flourishing, but now almost destroyed Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey? and what comfort can you have (if you survive) to behold it a spectacle of sorrow and astonishnent to its friends: of scorn, contempt, and horrible insulting to its enemies, who by all their industry could not effect what you have done for them? and which is worse, when poore <hi>England</hi> shall behold itself thus mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serable, and strongly chained under this condition, having nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther hopes nor meanes left to be repaired or recovered; for (if I much mistake not) your endeavours do tend to remove her fence and wall of government quite away, and to lay her waste, to take up and destroy her sluce, that the waters of comfort, both spirituall and temporall, in time may glide away; to what end else tends your striving to hinder and oppose such a Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in the Church as may effectually and piously secure the sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred truths of God (the least part whereof is farre more preci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous then our lives) from cursed mixtures, fantastick interpreta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, bold and blasphemous assertions, even to the visible and great impairing and decay of piety and righteousnesse? why else are all such impious persons, under pious pretences covered and kept warme and safe under your Independent wings? Why have you juggled and delaied to produce your own <hi>Modell of Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> the meane while Jesuitically dividing the people, increasing your party every where, and drawing after you many admirers of your selves, and your long promised Government, which nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther you nor they do understand?</p>
            <p>Time was, you joyned with us; you cride down Papists and their adherents cride up, and praid to God and man for a bles<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed Reformation; but now with you the wind is turn'd about; you cry up a formall declared <hi>Toleration</hi> to all persons, professions and consciences, and if in love and faithfulnesse we labour to
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:113763:3"/>hold and keep you out of this consuming fire, whereinto you are posting: you rave, and cry out <hi>persecution; persecution;</hi> judge if there be not reason thus to charge you.</p>
            <p>It hath beene said by some of your principall sticklers, that we ought to tolerate amongst us, not only false worshippers, but worshippers of false gods. What, will such a Reformation (or rather deformation) content you now? have yee utterly forgot, or refuse ye to remember the ground of this unnaturall war in refe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence to Religion; or have you lost your Religion amidst the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fusions which this war hath occasioned? Oh! what horrible Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sters willa declared <hi>Toleration</hi> bring in upon us, when a meer connivance hath produced so many great evils? but I beleeve you have some seduced followers, who mean better then their leaders and intend no harm to the publike, I mean as little to them.</p>
            <p>But you have your instruments of all sorts and sizes, you have some curious Artists and Ingeneares, who can lay plots, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour that conclusions and experiments of new medicines ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver before administred to the body politick of any Common-wealth may be tried upon this, not considering, or much caring whether it may operate to the recovery or the ruine of this sick State, if but hopefull to promote their designes; and are mighty studious and active to abuse the people in that most weighty work of electing Members into the <hi>House of Commons,</hi> crying up unfit men, and endeavouring in a surreptitious way to promote the election of such.</p>
            <p>And here the world may take notice of some late expressions of Master <hi>Peters</hi> who (being told at the Leager before <hi>Oxford,</hi> that whoever could gaine his favour, might be chosen a Member of Parliament) acknowledged that even at that time he had the disposing of two or three such places, and could conferre them upon such persons as he thought fit. Now let <hi>all</hi> judge whether any such power ought to reside in him, and if this be not a ready way to put peace farre from us, and to destroy us by a Law? But that God who hath wonderfully saved this poore Nation, I trust will blast those devices. You have those who strike at the face, nay at the very heart of <hi>Monarchy,</hi> at the validity of the regular and well-digested Votes of the high and honourable <hi>House of Peeres,</hi> and with unparaleld desperatenesse, strike at
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:113763:4"/>the very root of Parliaments, when either Lords or Commons do either vote or act any thing contrary to your ends and humors; And that not only whispered, but published to the world in print, with such invectives against the Parliament, as outstrips even <hi>Aulicus</hi> himself, and no wonder; for <hi>Ana-baptists &amp;c.</hi> do not so much oppose government, because it is of this or that frame, but because it is government, which impartially enjoynes subjection to a peaceable and just rule: Whereas they account themselves Kings, having a right to sway the Scepter as much as our Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne, and also Preists and Prophets, that all (from the Statesman to the Tinker, and from the Colonell to the Provos-marshall) may offer for, and preach to the people, as the spirit of faction and private designe shall dictate unto them; Nay, they rest not here; for they as well as Princes are sonnes of Adam, and know no rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son why a Chimney-sweeper, or a Broome-man, may not share in Common in the estates of their Brethren, yea and enjoy them rather then the right owners; for the good things of the world be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longe only unto them, being the only Saints as they reckon them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves. But this they cannot well compasse, untill they have tyed a Milstone about the neck of our Lawes, and throwne them into the bottom of the sea. Hath there not been of late bold adventures made to this purpose, by that tempestuous Incendiary, for which the right Honourable House of Lords most justly committed him to Newgate, against whom if there were a charge collected out of his owne speeches, writings, and other actions, I presume it would appeare such a peece of sedition, as never before came to light. And wise men are of opinion, that if he (and others like him) be not dealt with according to their demerit, it will prove of evill pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sident and consequence, and a great scandall to both the Honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Houses.</p>
            <p>You are fol of those who corrupt the doctrines of the sacred Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures, and not content that your selvs only should do so, but strive that all men may run into the same condemnation with you. And so far have you proceeded herein, that many simple ones are mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led; and not one principle of our saith left, but by some or other, is either blasphemously denyed, or Atheistically questioned.</p>
            <p>But blessed be God there are yet some who stand and will (by Gods assistance) still stand betwixt you and the enjoyment of
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:113763:4"/>your pride and lust; Though you work and threaten very hard, covering all with fairest pretences, like him that puts a faire glove upon foule hands. But let me tell you, no hypocrisie is so hatefull to God as that which mounteth most high towards him in pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence, and yet in effect and intentionally, centereth it self in the bottom of our own cisternes.</p>
            <p>You complain much of our <hi>Brethren of Scotland,</hi> as being guilty of great crimes and bad ends, &amp;c. What those are, and how they can appeare, I am yet to learne; but this I know, that if they love themselves (which you are apt to say they do too much) they must be honest and true to their Covenant; for providence hath so or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered matters, that they can benefit by no other meanes; yet it's much more comfortable, that they are faithfull to God, his Covenant and cause, out of love to him, and conscience of their duty, which hath been abundantly testified; And yet all this nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther hath, nor can satisfie that unreasonablenesse of prejudicate and malicious mindes.</p>
            <p>Tell me; did not you (if you are not a Romish Jusuit and do act the English Sectary) rejoyce in them, and blesse God for their exceeding love which brought them in, so to hazard all theirs, to five us and ours? have they not been serviceable, might they not have been lesse burdensome, and would gladly have been much more usefull, if they had received supplies necessary for such At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheivments? What people could have been more constant, lesse griveous? What temporations have they resisted? Standing by us like a brazen wall, when we doubted almost every h<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> amongst our selves; the <hi>Oxford</hi> charmer being so prevalent, to draw so many great and wise men from all their estates interests and dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rest relations, both in Country; City, and even from the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament it self. with what difficulties have they contended, and still do? Under what reproaches and discouragements have they labored? and yet with what wisedom, moderation, and patience, have they undergon them all, to the shame and wonder of their adversaries? For shame therefore lay by designe, which will not suffer you to see the wood for trees. See and thankfully acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge the goodnesse of God to this Nation by them, and he will yet make them a greates blessing.</p>
            <p>Also the Ministers of the Assembly, and Sion Colledge, and all
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:113763:5"/>other the godly Presbyterian Ministers, do heare (nay the right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eous God doth heare and remember, all those reproaches and scan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalls, which you and your party most unjustly dodayly forge and vent against them. Are not you one of them that deny the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority of the word, and with it all Ordinances? If you be not so grosse, there are many (whom you labour to uphold in their Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours) are, whose practise is to bring the Ministers into contempt, and then the Ministry and Ordinances with them; And as a ready way to further that devillish designe, they cry down Tithes (which from the Primitive times, both in our own and other Christian Kingdomes, have been by many Lawes setled upon the Ministry, as the most equall, most regular, and most agreeable way to the word of God) an evident demonstration whereof hath been shewed in those petitions brought up out of <hi>Hariford</hi> and <hi>Buckingham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shires.</hi> The inhabitants of which Counties have been drawn unto it, not out of any principle of Religion and Conscience, but of ignorance and covetousnesse. Though the active Emissaries of the Sectaries have had an other designe in it, <hi>viz.</hi> by impoverishing the Ministers, to drive them away, or make them contempti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, that so they might gain opportunity to thrust in corrupt and Mechanick Teachers, and the more quietly set up that vain and ridiculous Idoll, I meane the monster <hi>Toleration,</hi> which soon after it is up, will fall, and breake, to the ruine of it self, and all the worshippers thereof.</p>
            <p>The City of <hi>London</hi> also hath been very sensible of, and much suffered under those many traducing and malicious invectices of some which like the fruit of vipers, have struck at the life, and gnawn at the bowells of her that bred and nourished them. Is it imaginable with what wonder and contempt, all wise men in this and future ages, will behold this selfe-destroying and ungrat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full generation?</p>
            <p>What hath this faithfull City (which God hath inclined to be a Sanctuary and a nurse, opening her armes to embrace all di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stressed religious persons from all places) yet deserved no better from you and your associats?</p>
            <p>I reckon it superfluous to enumerate the many mighty thing wherein God hath made this city and Citizens instrumentall in the view of all men, having been even prodigall of their blood,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:113763:5"/>and of all things precious to men, to maintain the cause of God and this Parliament, and that without private ends; for they neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected themselves and all those frequent offers of additionall power, benefit, and priviledg, which yet they were invited to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive, and might <hi>then</hi> have had for asking for, with promise also of some extraordinary mark of honour, to proclaim the constant and unparraleld faithfullnesse of this city to all succeeding generati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. And <hi>the eyes of all Christendome</hi> expect the performance; <hi>for my part</hi> I rest assured of the full performance hereof, maugre all the malice and supplantations of Incendiaries. And tis worth obser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation that this City did, and do, humbly acquiesce in the said promises, <hi>untill</hi> the enemy be supprest; Minding the publike ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, and the Obligation of their duty and Covenant, continuing to act accordingly, from which by divine assistance they resolve not to vary.</p>
            <p>What ground is there then for any malicious minde to think, much lesse to publish that horrid woe and alas, London will ruine us, <hi>London</hi> beginns to decline the Parliament, <hi>London</hi> begins to close with the King, <hi>London</hi> is fild with Malignants Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage, <hi>London</hi> demonstrates to the Parliaments prejudice?</p>
            <p>Can <hi>London</hi> be imagined so far to forfeit her reason, as to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come destructive to the publike, like your self and your crue, whose eyes are so far dazled with an <hi>ignis fatuus,</hi> or new lights, that you have lost the faculty of discerning betwix truth and errour, peace and war, and the issues and consequences of them all? Hence it is, that you judge an humble and faithfull Peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and Remonstrance (carrying within it, its own justification, against envy it self) to tend to the Parliaments prejudice.</p>
            <p>To comply with the King in an evill sence, to the guilty of the foule crime of malignancy, to decline the Parliament, and to ruine the Kingdom; <hi>What man!</hi> is it become a character of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lignancy to Petition that a forme of Church-government accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the Word of God, and the example of the best reform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Churches, may with all speed be perfected and confirmed by the civill sanction of Authority? That Schismaticks, Hereticks, and seducing teachers be effectually suppressed, and all good means used to make up the sad breaches in this our <hi>Sion?</hi> Why then do you not charge an endeavour of ruine upon those 300.
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:113763:6"/>and more, learned and godly Divines of <hi>Suffolk</hi> and <hi>Essex,</hi> who subscribed a Petition to this purpose as well as <hi>London?</hi> You might as soone, and (in some respects) sooner have been belei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved. Certainly this immoderate Replyer and his companions are wilfully ignorant, and will not know, weak in judgement, or strangers, and do not know the <hi>Interest of London.</hi> Should <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don</hi> ruine the Kingdom together with it self, who is so great a part, and hath so great an interest in the whole? Consider what, and how considerable <hi>London</hi> is, what lands in every County this City and Citizens have a right in, as in this Kingdom so in <hi>Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land?</hi> How doth this City by themselves and their stock carry on the home and forraign trade of the whole Kingdom in the greatest measure? and the greatest part of the Shipping which are as walls to this Island, are they not built, imployed, and main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained by this City? How many friends and allies hath this City in all parts of the Kingdom,<note place="margin">This Interest being recipro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call.</note> who are very dear and precious to them? How effectuall is their example, and hath ever been to induce and engage the Kingdom to preserve it self, the cause of God, and this Parliament? May I not call this city a principall vitall part of these three united Kingdoms, a support to friends, a scourge and terrour to enemies, forraign and domestick? and although you grutch and esteeme every little power as too much for <hi>London,</hi> yet in all this and much more (through the goodnes and power of our God) <hi>London</hi> will shame its adversaries, whilst it self will stand firme as a rock. Thus is it most clear to wise men that <hi>London</hi> cannot comply with any <hi>(either high or low)</hi> in plotting the ruine of the Kingdom; therefore cease to reproach <hi>London, and remember</hi> that neither person or faction ever pros<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pered long that did thus provoke it.</p>
            <p>Possibly you may here object, that you speak not thus of <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don,</hi> but of a party there.</p>
            <p>For answer by the way, Why then do you contradict your selfe, saying in your immoderate Reply, <hi>London</hi> will ruine us, <hi>London</hi> will do this and that? But to answer more fully (what party do you mean) I beleeve and affirme that the cloathing of all the companies of <hi>London</hi> (which I suppose you name the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy collective) unlesse it be one man of a hundred, do most hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tily concur with the <hi>Remonstrance,</hi> which hath beene, and will be
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:113763:6"/>sufficiently evidenced to the world, when authority shall please to call them together; and not they only (which yet is most considerable) but the farre greatest part of all the rest, free-men and others. A good demonstration whereof is that Petition of the Inhabitants and free-men of <hi>London</hi> presented to the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-Councell, <hi>June</hi> 23. and subscribed by many thousand hands. If you meane the Common-Councell, is it not the representative of the City? much like as the Parliament is of the Kingdom. And as it is treason in any man to exasperate, or to endeavour to raise the Kingdom represented against the Kingdom representa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive; So is it sedition at least, and tends higher, to endeavour to raise the City represented against the City representative, espe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially when grounded upon your foure meer pretences and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geries, not worth a word of answer, and know that the procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings of the representative of this City, are wise, regular, and faithfull, and can endure the barking at of such as you are, and yet never fall from their element or principles; and doubtlesse have, and still ought to have as much power to conclude this Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty in their Votes, as when for the service of this Parliament they charged the <hi>fifty Subsidies upon themselves</hi> and it. If you mean a party in the Common-Councell; for answer, are there not some in all Councels (the Parliament it selfe not excepted) who speak and appeare more in all the debates, then many o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers do? and yet the silent persons may be very usefull, and may discerne as farre into the matters debated as any; if then they concurre and Vote therein, and the major part con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude it <hi>(Without forestalling or surprisals)</hi> is it not past ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception? It may be that you are troubled that all Members in Councels are not Speakers, like to the members of your new se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parated and confused congregations. But the great quarrell is, that the Common-Councell doth not concurre with you in your destructive designes. No, nor was it ever in their intentions so to do; nor can they, it being so contrary unto those two grand obliging principles of conscience and interest. They still act by the same rule and motives they did, when they first took arms against the common enemy; And are most unjustly charged when they are told that they decline the Parliament, or their owne first principles; <gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o certainly, the defection is in you and
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:113763:7"/>your party, who like a man intoxicated, thinks the house turnes round, when the fault is in his owne addle head; or like a man rowed upon the water, who fancies that the bancks move as well as the boate, but the bancks remove not, nor doth the Common-Councell (although most of your party are gone) from their first just grounds; only their opinions are altered touching some persons of your faction, who have given sufficient cause to all wise men to dislike their courses.</p>
            <p>Indeed you have taken a great liberty to use (or rather abuse) this City, the governors and government thereof at your plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure; one Sectary most impudently enters the City, and publish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth a Proclamation in contempt of its government, by the same reason he may to morrow in like manner publish (if he could obtaine it) that which should utterly and instantly ruine the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, this city, and all the inhabitants thereof. Others of you to gaine subscriptions to your late Petition, did use false and indirect wayes and meanes to the great scandall of this City; o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwise that inconsiderable number of (for the most part) in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>considerable persons, had not beene much more then halfe so ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny; one of your number, <hi>viz.</hi> that Ubiquitary Master <hi>Peters,</hi> hath exprest his diligence like to an unwearied Champion for evill, chiefly labouring to serve himself and his party under the faire pretence of serving the publike.</p>
            <p>Amongst the multitude of his unworthy prancks, I shall only instance this one; namely, his getting a Purse into his hands to buy Meddals for the incouragement of deserving Souldiers, which Meddals he having prepared, refuseth of late to conferre that badge of honour upon any, though never so worthy, unlesse they subscribe for a contribution towards the maintenance of the separate Churches in <hi>London;</hi> having by his seducements pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vailed farre therein amongst the Commanders of the Army, discouraging thereby the Presbyterians, and discovering the number of each party in the said Army; for what ends others may gueffe, but himself knoweth best: Others (nay few but) are, violent and turbulent disturbers of the peace, despisers of autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, arraigning and condemning the Courts, Lawes, Governors, and government of the City and Kingdom, making your selves (though most unfit) sole judges and interpreters both of the
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:113763:7"/>Lawes of god and man, and what not? Truly considering all this, it would be no honour for this City to be in favo<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> with, or commended by, either you or your party; and 'tis fit it should beare a share of your injurious reproaches, with our Brethren of <hi>Scotland,</hi> the Assembly of Divines, and other honest men, yea, all the Reformed Churches, who are all enemies alike to your ir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>regular and skeptick proceedings.</p>
            <p>I have heard you commended for your activity; truly I cannot joyne therein, unlesse you were zealous in a good matter; but it is said that you have much advantaged your designe thereby; but consider, the swifter the deviation is the more tedious &amp; difficult will the returne be; Its well knowne you have some furious dri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers, or desperate sticklers, whom I may compare to a busie pet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty-fogger, imployed in a suite against a whole County, who (whilst the County or any for them are either absent or negli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent) by false suggestions and misinformations obtaines an order of court against them; But when the County hears of it, disco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers the fallacy, and rightly informs the Court, nulls the order, and recovers dammages; expect the issue to be such; for beleeve it your vizards will off, your fallacious and false dealings appeare more and more every day; Proceed therefore in your nimble courses as long as you can, since you hate to be wiser. The City cannot steere by your Compasse; great bodies move slowly, and honest men deale fairly; the City may not use your way of daily and undue sollicitations at <hi>Westminster,</hi> nor impoly scurrilous and abusive Pamphlet-makers, who labour to charme the people into a good opinion of an ill cause, and turne all the waters of praise and profit into your Cistern, nor send Emissaries to stirre up the people to Petition for your Independent licencious liberty; and with Pamphlets and other Books scattered and delivered gratis into all or most parts of the Kingdom; and Preachers also of all trades and crafts sent to gaine Proselytes, and to poy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son the judgements of the people, nor buy men over to them with money or gaine, &amp;c. Nor labour with the Army <hi>(whilst the Sword is in their hands)</hi> to Petition the Parliament, nor use packing and juggling courses, nor lies<note n="*" place="margin">See Rev. 22.15</note> and falsities, nor vaine bragges of the greatnesse of a party, when indeed they are no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, some few sticklers being laid aside; your whole number
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:113763:8"/>being a sort of giddie people, made up of byased and engaged men, and some strangers, rash Youth, silly Women and Maidens, yet by such are we thus perplexed, and the Kingdoms in danger to be ruined, by your troubling our waters; as if in calme and quiet streames, you could catch no fish, and therefore you refuse no meanes which may disturbe our present peace, or prevent an establishment of this distressed Kingdom therein.</p>
            <p>These practises appeare extreame odious in the eyes of all true hearted <hi>Presbyterians,</hi> nor need they such unlawfull helps. No, their Cause and Ends are so good, as will admit of no bad meanes to carry them on. The prime meanes which they <hi>yet</hi> use, is by humble and hearty addresses to Heaven, and to the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: To the first they have a liberty as Christians; to the second, as true English-men and free Cittizens, who have laid all at stake by its request and command, to serve and save the Kingdom.</p>
            <p>And by the same justice and reason you quarrell their liberty to the <hi>Second,</hi> you may to the <hi>First;</hi> and be so charitable (in the practise of your new large liberty of conscience) as to rob and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prive them of all hopes and meanes both in heaven and earth, to free them from those insupportable burdens which you labour to lay, and binde upon them, evento the breaking of their backs and hearts; insomuch that you may well wonder why they go not up in multitudes, to crave justice against some of your Champians, as formerly they did against other Incendiaries. But remember<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their former ill tempered zeal, and their present requisite duty, they intend to forbeare a while. But you have not lost all love to your selves (as you say the City hath, by joyning in a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>signe to its ruine) for although you will not allow the Metropo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lis of England to Petition regularly, yet particular persons of your party may, and that for publike ends too; and not only Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monstrate, but raile against, and that to the faces of the Peers and Judges of the land, and that in open Court too, with incredible insolency, as that disturber of the first magnitude hath lately done.</p>
            <p>Was is it malice or ignorance, or a mixture of both, that mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved you to charge our Remonstrance with the termes, First, of an unparaleld Remonstrance. Secondly, exceeding the power of our Charter. And Thirdly, receiving its rise from Royallists and
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:113763:8"/>Malignants? To the first I answer, I am confident you cannot but know, that severall Remonstrances have been presented to this Parliament, by persons far lesse considerable then the Common-Councell of <hi>London.</hi> I shall only minde you of that presented to the Honourable House of Commons, in <hi>December,</hi> 1642. by Sir <hi>David Watkins,</hi> and Master <hi>Shute,</hi> and accompanyed by three of your much admired friends, Master <hi>Burrowes,</hi> Master <hi>Peters,</hi> and Master <hi>Goodwin;</hi> containing, as I conceive, divers things of a far higher nature in some respects, then the highest clause of our Remonstrance, and yet was graciously and thankfully received by that Honourable House. to the second I answer; I confesse I never read the Charter, but am informed that we have not in the least exceeded the bounds thereof: But admit we did pray for something which could not cleerly arise from any branch thereof; Could the prevision of former Parliaments, perfectly provide us all requisites for safety to the end of the world; so as that it should become a crime in us to pray to this Parliament for any addition or alteration, or for them to grant it; especially con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sidering the great disturbances in the Church, the transaction and mutations in the State, which these wars have produced, and wherein this City hath been cheifly used? All which might well put us into a necessity of craving something more then we had before. To the third I answer, it is very probable that Malig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nants as well as other men are well pleased, that we are true to our Covenant in that article which concernes our Loyalty to his Majestie: If this be an offence, truly I cannot consent to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>move it, although scrupled at by never so many pretended tender consciences. Yet do I most earnestly pray, that for the honour and benefit both of King and People, such due and honourable bounds be set, that neither prerogative, nor any other power may be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to grow monstrous any more.</p>
            <p>The pursuance of our duty in this lawfull and necessary thing, possibly causeth many to be ready to close with us, who other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise would not. But our confidence is not in multitudes, but in the goodnesse and faithfullnesse of our God. However if it were unlawfull, it would be almost as bad as your great engine <hi>Tolera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> which calls into your aid, not only Malignants, but Papists, Atheists, Libertines, Turks, Jews, Infidels, Blasphemers, and all
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:113763:9"/>sorts of Hereticks; each man expecting an indulgence from Pope <hi>Toleration;</hi> Still to enjoy his <hi>Dallilah,</hi> and keep the sweet morsell hidden under his tongue, which we well know will prove as a canker, eating out the power of Religion, and the peace of the Kingdoms, and will expose us as a prey to the teeth of some wol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vish enemies, who have long waited for such an opportunity to devoure us.</p>
            <p>And know farther (you immoderate Replyer, and your fellow Libellers) that the Magistracy of <hi>London</hi> doe, and will doe their duties in opposing you, in your destructive waies, and must not be checkt, or directed by all, or any of you. What the Authority of Parliaments is, they acknowledge, and reverence its just Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority. And here you force me to say, that they have done and furfered, (and still doe) so much to preserve it inviolable, that it almost exceeds the power of Art, fully to declare to the world, their famous services; Consider what vast summs of treasure did <hi>London</hi> voluntarily contribute, when either they must do it, or all must perish. <hi>Amicus certus in re incerta cernitur.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Which borrowed treasure will no doubt (for the honour and credit of Parliaments) certainly be repaid. Hath it not long and willingly borne <hi>any</hi> impositions? And doth it not still pay fifteen thousand pounds a week, or there about, for custome and excise, besides all other Loanes, Taxes and impositions, even to admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration? In a word, have they not preferred obedience to the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands of Parliament (both ordinary and extraordinary) above their very lives? and yet now to be thus charged, and sawcily checkt, and directed by a single Sectary. Oh! horrible pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sumption and impudency; in which black Arts, the Sectaries of these times are noted to be the greatest proficients.</p>
            <p>Nay, you proceed, and tell the Magistracy of <hi>London,</hi> that the people (who they represent) will not own the Remonstrance, nor will stand by them. But then, and how came you to know it, so as thus positively to give the sence of the people? And what doe you meane by the peoples standing by them? It seems to me you intend or desire a new war; that you will again force them to the use of their sword; if so, accursed from God be your de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>signe. The City intends it not; they desire, that now God having so blest indeavours, as that they may have Religion and Peace set<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:113763:9"/>and secured to them and to posterity, that no time or op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity be lost to effect it; and that all impediments be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moved, and the long prayed for mercies embraced, with all hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and perpetuall thankfullnesse to the God of our salvation, and all due thankfullnesse to the Parliament, and every faithfull instrument.</p>
            <p>But if you only meane that the people will not approve of the Remonstrance, then you see to your hearts grief that the people of <hi>London</hi> (or the body Collective, as you term them) do and will adhere to the Common-Councell and their Remon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strance according to their duty. And how can it be otherwise? Are not all the Members of Common-Councell, men of their own annuall electing from among themselves, and engaged both in conscience and interest to be faithfull? Do not all their <hi>Votes and Acts,</hi> effectually engage <hi>themselves,</hi> without any freedom or <hi>priviledge,</hi> in person or estate, more then any person represented by them hath? And have they not ever been unchangeably true to this trust? And lastly, you tell us of the dangerous tendency of our Remonstrance and Petition, wherein you flourish, and shew your Art and envy; proving nothing, dealing only in generals, as deceivers use to do. Truly I shall declare both to you, and the whole world, what the Remonstrance tends to; and shall appeale to every honest man to judge, whether it be not so: It tends and strives to unite the Kingdomes in the way of God, that they and their seed may enjoy the blessed fruits of a happie union; even, Religion, Righteousnesse and Peace, and abundance of all good things.</p>
            <p>All which so beautifull and desireable happinesse (in probabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity) the Kingdoms might soon enjoy, did not you, and your party raise mountains of opposition in the way; Remoraes one after another; which but lately was the work of Papists and Malig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nants; neither conscience, nor Covenants, nor Lawes of God or man, being able to hold you from your destructive wayes; which threaten as fatall and as certain ruine to the Kingdoms, (if you prevaile to obtain your desired Toleration) as did theirs. Yet with the strumpet your wipe your mouth, and say, what have I done? Falsly and maliciously, shifting the evill issue of your owne actions, upon the honest and plaine hearted Presbyterians; and
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:113763:10"/>chargeing them, that they would not have an honest man to live amongst them, and for all your great tendernesse of conscience, can forge reproachfull names for them, calling them Adamits, Remonstrators, Persecutors, and what not; asperfing, and rashly censuring every honest man that stands in your way: But if his integrity be so famous, that none of your diet will fasten upon him, then you commend his good meaning, but insinuate his weaknesse, and tell the world of the patronage of abused simpli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>city; and being drawn from his duty, by the finenesse, and arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice of impostors, under the specious shew of Reformation and uniformity, although probably, he is more able to discover the ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifice of impostors, and more willing to eschew their danger, then the most admired person of your faction, with the help of all your new lights; whereby, and with your fine specious shew and arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice, you have more prevailed to dazle the eyes of men, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>settle and disturbe the Kingdome in foure years, then fourescore yeares of the enjoyment of the Gospell could establish it. Nay you are become so hardned in this sinne, that you seem to rejoyce, and to blesse your selves in such practises; nor must we so much as reprove you for them, under the pain of being accounted per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>secutors of the Saints, for such as you only are the faithfull friends and servants of the Parliament; whereas experience shews it to be your dayly practise to Maligne and scandalize those who are so in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, for no other reason, but because they cannot approve of your opinions and practises; yet you expect it as a duty from the Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byterians, to joyne with you in love and affection, although they differ in opinion, and do much exclaime against them for the least failing therein; whilst you and your party take a liberty to pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice the contrary, urging that we should have a constant respect to the rule (wherein you do well) but you will be your own rule, and make Lawes for your selves: and herein I could offer some weighty and pregnant instances, but presuming they cannot be so soone forgot, I forbeare. And notwithstanding all your great pretences, I may (without breach of charity) say, there was never such hypocrisie (in the matters both of God and man) exprest since the world was first founded, as at this day; for there was ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver so much pretended and sworne, that piety, justice, and peace, should be advanced and settled; and yet never such corrupting of
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:113763:10"/>truths, never such sleighting and underming of the power of god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linesse; never such loosnesse and licentiousnesse, as in Doctrine, so in mens manners, never more injustice practised, never were those precious jewels of peace and order more needfull, and lesse valued; never such driving on of base and by-ends, nor such un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>just and indirect means and wayes used and attempted by some Sectaries, to effect those ends: It would be to tedious to particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larise the persons and actions, nor shall I need it, being so fully al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready done by others; let any indifferent eye observe your daily practises in all places, and peruse those heaps of odious Pamphlets written by many of your selves: let any man also but view (a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongst others) that dangerous Pamphlet called a Remonstrance of many thousand Citizens and other free-borne people of <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland</hi> occasioned by the late imprisonment of Master <hi>Lilburn.</hi> Wherein the Parliament is arraigned, and each of the three E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>states of the Kingdom debased and extremely vilified, and all endeavours used to divide, and thereby to destroy them; whilst the giddy people, or confused multitude are cried up, and pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced in the Throne to judge their Judges, who can hope for no mercy from them, there being no such Tyrant as are the people, when once they can get the power into their hands. <hi>Bellua mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torum Captium multitudo.</hi> Those truths published in the Books of Mr. <hi>Thomas Edwards,</hi> Mr. <hi>Bayly,</hi> and divers godly Divines, and other honest men, published on purpose <hi>(as I do this)</hi> to unmaske you, and to give a caveat to well-meaning people, who are apt to be cheated with your counterfeit coynes, and great pretence of holinesse, liberty, and pure Ordinance, the old engines and arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice of Hereticks and Schismaticks, whereby they use to facilitate their work.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Religion</hi> and <hi>Liberty</hi> are indeed the two great Arguments wherewith wise men ought to be much taken and affected, and we heare much talk of them from you; O that I could not say that little else but talke is to be discerned from the greatest part of you; you cry up Religion, and with the same breach do plead for Blasphemers, Hereticks, and other enemies, who strike at the very root of Religion; and when you are about to make the people worse then slaves, (because slves to you) you cry <hi>salus po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puli,</hi> and the liberties of Englishmen, whereof Master <hi>Lilburne,</hi>
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:113763:11"/>and such other, expect to be the sole Judges, and not the Lawes or constitutions of England; for against them they do daily de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claime with insufferable insolencie, as if the wholsome Lawes of the Kingdome did debarre them from any part of their just li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty. But the liberty you and they so much contend for, I e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>steeme not worth the having, because its an enemy to Peace, and it is against the nature of it to reside any where but in, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongst troublesome and confused times, places, and persons; and furnisheth men with desperate and irregular incouragements, resolutions, and practises tending to equalize, subvert, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>found persons, families; yea, all ranks, orders, and degrees of persons and societies, Churches, Kingdomes, and Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealths: these, and such as these are the fruits of this liberty, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording as it hath beene lately used by some of your sraternity, even to the exposing of us to the pits brink of another warre, worse then the former bloudy warre, which yet is not past over, the skars thereof being still visible, and our wounds running, bleeding, and festering; &amp; that not only in reference to the bodies of our dear Country men and Brethren, but to the generall state of three languishing Kingdomes; yet have you no bowels of pity and compassion towards the one or the other, but pressing hard forwards towards destruction you infect and mislead the judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of people by all meanes possible, straining your parts in so<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phisticall (and often sottish) arguments, and when you meet with any who begin to discov<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r your deceits, O how you shuffle and shift, like the Papist, from one argument to another and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude nothing; using a forme of fine words and high phrases to small purpose, more then to amuse the standers by; and when you are so closely followed by clear Scripture argument, as that your reason is at last gaspe, how do you then straine and abuse the holy word of God with false glosses, and will owne no interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pretation, but such as will sure with your ends, claiming a liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to give your own sence thereof, though it be sometimes such as was never heard of in the world before, and when some of you have beene told so, you have fathered your blasphemy upon the Spirit of God, as if he did convey this new light as a peculiar gift unto you; and in all your contestations wherein I have been a witnesse, you labour to place a right and power in each man to
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:113763:11"/>judge of truth, and to interpret the whole word of God, or any part thereof as shall seem good to his own opinion; Why then do you not deliver this to the world as a principle of your new light? <hi>That true Religion is nothing else but what each man judgeth to be so,</hi> thereby making every parcell of sinfull dust the judge of that Sacred Word which undoubtedly shall one day approve, acquit, or condemne all the severall sorts of creatures both in heaven and earth, bringing that dreadfull curse upon your selves for adding to, or taking any thing from that blessed Word which is of a most superlative esteeme with the holy Angels, and by them acknowledged to be a most deep and glorious mystery, and whereinto they willingly pry; yet you have those (most dread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full it is to speak it) who have said they are able to compose as good a Scripture, and deny the truth and authority of this Word; and abundance more such cursed blasphemies, that I tremble to think of them, and dare not transcribe them, but they are too well known.</p>
            <p>It may be you will object, that you are neither Anabaptist, Antinomian, Brownist, Seeker, Heretick, or Blasphemer, nor a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of the rest of that numerous rabble, but a meere Indepen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, who like not the Presbyterian government, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Answ.</hi> And why not the Presbyterian government? In the judgement of the best Divines its most agreeable to the word of God, 'tis practised in all the Reformed Churches, it hath beene tried and searched by the best men in divers ages, and hath gained the testimony of the best Government; the Parliament hath or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained and declared for it; and should they now vouch safe you a Government of your owne framing, both you and your party would be as much unsetled and to seeke, as you have been all this while; and as those divided and sub-sub-divided separate Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches in <hi>Holland</hi> ever were; and will you value your Independent nullity, before this so good a Government? Which, though good, I beleeve you neither like it, nor Monarchy, nor House of Peeres, nor Ministry, nor our Brethren of Scotland, nor the City of London, nor that there are so many Presbyterians in the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, nor in <hi>Plain English,</hi> any thing but an Anarchy both in Church and State, notwithstanding the Nationall Covenant, and all those other great obligations which lye upon you to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary.</p>
            <pb n="20" facs="tcp:113763:12"/>
            <p> I answer further: although you be not an Anabaptist, &amp;c. yet being an Independent, you are all those in effect; for if you and other Independents were not, those other Sects, either could not be at all, or not so hurtfull; for you plead for them, protect, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive and harbor them: but remember the Proverb, A receiver is worse then a theif.</p>
            <p>Againe, if ye be not yet properly one of them, take heed, for you soone may be, having laid your selfe in Satans high-way, I meane that of <hi>Toleration;</hi> and 'tis great oddes, if spirituall pride, and the craft and diligence of deceivers, do not betray you to the embracing of one errour in Doctrine; and when one of them hath gained admittance, it will usher in all the rest after it, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lesse God mightily prevent: and therefore say not, that an errour in judgement is a light thing,; for as the judgement is, such will the practice be, the conviction of the mind being the mother of ra<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ionall actions, much like, as Independency is the mother of all those Sects and Schismes which so annoy us, and threaten the ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ruine of all things precious to us.</p>
            <p>Oh! therefore consider I beseech you, before it be too late all yee that are either unsetled, or already mis-led by the sleights and cunning craftinesse of those who lie in wait to deceive.</p>
            <p>What dishonour you do to God, what damage will accrue to his Church and these three Kingdomes, yea to your owne soules by serving the ends, and strengthning the hands of such, who by their tenents and practises do evidence to the world (notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing their other pretences) that they are enemies to God and good men, whose constant practises are against truth, peace, uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and good government; and that your may escape their snare, observe their cunning, their faire and specious shewes, pretences and promises. But it would be needlesse to repeate all the glosses, pretences, and faire promises with which they use to deceive the simple; and to wash off those blots where with they have beene most deservedly charged. I shall only instance in their pretended<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly moderate Master <hi>Burroughs</hi> his Vindication against Mr, <hi>Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards</hi> his two Books called <hi>Gangraena</hi> and <hi>Antapologia,</hi> whereby their practises have most worthily beene discovered and confuted; which Book, because it cannot be well answered, therefore they must be impatiently railed at, and all endeavours used to asperse
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:113763:12"/>the person of that faithfull friend of truth. And in the 24. page of Mr. <hi>Burroughs</hi> his Book, he accun's it an injury that Indepen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents are said to be such as would have no Government, but that all Heresies, &amp;c. be tolerated.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Answ.</hi> Let any judicious indifferent man judge whether the protecting, pleading for, and palliating the faults of Blasphemers, Hereticks and Sectaries, mediating and soliciting for a Tolerati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, or at least connivance for them, and the Independents rec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>koning all said or done against themselves, which is said, writ, or done against such Sectaries; I say, judge whether this charge be not just upon them. and is not the protection and toleration of Schismaticks contained in the very nature of Independency it selfe? And here let sad experience speak what lesse hath (but the beginnings of) Independence produced, and what monstrous effects may we expect from it, if tolerated? But for the said Book in generall it promiseth much, and I confesse I did expect more from M. <hi>Burroughs,</hi> then light irritating and personall discourses, for which he blames others even in the same Book, using glosses and insinuations, but leaves unanswered that which sticks and wil stick upon him and his party; yet cries out of Mr. <hi>Edwards</hi> as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing faulty, whereas nothing appeareth but his zeale for God and his truth against Blasphemers and licencious persons, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in Mr. <hi>Burroughs</hi> ought to joyne with him, if he were as he desi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth to be accounted.</p>
            <p>Observe also now of late their great threatnings, saying, that if we oppose their wayes, we shall offend God, the Parliament, and the Army: To discover the untruth hereof; I affirms, and it is certain, that its no offence to God, but a duty we owe unto him, to vindicate his name and truth against Blasphemy, Errour, and contempt; nor to the Parliament or any other good men to rescue and plead for the Lawes, Government, Order and Peace of the Kingdoms from ruine an I violation: nor to the Armies that we contend by Word for the preservation of all those, yea the same precious things, which they with the Sword did or ought to have sought for.</p>
            <p>Certainly it is a high presumption in all erroneous Sectaries to render the Parliament and Armies under such a terrible notion, as if their opinions and affections were altered, and turned from their
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:113763:13"/>best and most considerable friends, whereby jealousies are fomen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, the hands of the Parliament weakned, our enemies encoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, and the whole Kingdom extremly disturbed and endangered; And a strange impudency it is in the said Sectaries to patronize their Errours, and the maintenance of them upon God, the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, and the Army; and 'tis contrary to reason, as well as Religion, that it should be so. Can Almighty God approve of any practice which is contrary to his own holy will? Or can <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glands</hi> Parliament countenance any endeavours tending to ruine the publike, who are so highly entrusted, sworn, and bound both in conscience and interest to preserve it, even to the utmost hazard of all they either have or are? And have they not most worthily decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to the world, and sworn to the mighty God &amp; Judge of heaven and earth, for such a Reformation, which shall not only discounte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, but <hi>extirpate all Schisme and Heresie, as well as Ropery and Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lacy, and what ever else shall be found contrary to sound Doctrin and the power of godlines,</hi> we hope the Parliament (by Gods assistance) will effect. when that good and necessary Discipline of the Church can be settled, and the great work of saving the Kingdom give them leave to intend it; Or can our Army who have so gallant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly stood in defence of Religion and Liberty, now render them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves for ever infamous, by being the Champions of irreligion, and licencious Toleration, as some Sectaries would faine have us to beleeve? No, we would not entertain such thoughts of any of them, who have done so well formerly.</p>
            <p>But I like not that the Sectaries should thus mention the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my as a distinct state of the Kingdom; for, our Kingdoms govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment knows but three Estates, namely King, Lords, and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons, which (without addition or fundamentall alteration) we are bound to preserve inviolable against all men whatsoever, as the best Government this day extant in the world, which being altered or confounded, will cause great and continuall distruban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and at last utter ruine to these three Kingdoms.</p>
            <p>Now therefore if that which you so much contend for, be chiefely but a lawfull liberty of conscience, and to serve God in purity, use no unlawfull or impure means to accomplish those good ends; for all wise men will conclude, that whilst the means you use are bad, your ends and aimes cannot be good, Many of
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:113763:13"/>your evill practises I have now hinted, more (as reserved) lye in the deck; but I shall observe two things very notorious in your party.</p>
            <p>First, that you have ever born as final a part of the publike bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den as might be, whilst many of you have made shew of doing much but indeed have built you houses out of the Kingdoms ruines; yet when any publike work is done at the charge of others, you chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenge all the honour as being due to you.</p>
            <p>The second is, in your not being content thus unjustly to Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nopolize the praises due to others, but strive to destroy even them and their reputations, by infamous and false imputations, report<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that they drive on the Kings designe, and carry a complyance with the Kings Declarations, and what not; whereas, they, of all others, have appeared most free from self-ends and base designes, your own consciences being judges.</p>
            <p>All these things you do, whereby our peace is deferred, and those blessed endeavours which tend to settlement, rendred fruit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lesse; whilst the rents and ruines of the Church continually grow more desperate and irrepairable: The Kingdoms impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verished by the mighty charge and spoyle of an <hi>intostine</hi> bloudy war, and polluted with the <hi>guilt</hi> thereof, and the spirits of men still more exasperated one against another, which threatneth a se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond and a worse war then the former. and whilst forraigne States do more and more draine away, and deprive us both of our Trade and our Treasure, whereby the Kingdoms are weakned, and strangers sitted and strengthned for the first opportunity to destroy both your selves and us; consider the many clouds which hang over us, and amongst others, that of the Prince his going out of the Kingdom; Historians can tell you, that formerly such accidents have cost dear: Mathematicians will lay that so great an Ecclipse is (or may be) fatall; reason and experience tels us, that he is not amongst our best friends.</p>
            <p>Whilst we are divided, we are weak, and the longer our divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion is, the more our weaknesse will be, and then will our enemies delight to show their strength most, when ours appears to bee least.</p>
            <p>Forbear therefore to do any thing tending to disunite us, and
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:113763:14"/>poure forth no more Oyle upon the flame, but into the wounds of these distressed bleeding Kingdoms; let us close ere it be too late, and then probably our foes will turn our friends (at least in shew) however we shall be better able to defend the Nation from their lust and fury. Be perswaded to that end to labour after u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity in judgement, flatter not your selves; for it contradicts Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture, reason, and experience, that there can be a blessed concord in affection amongst Christians, when there are such vast diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rences in opinion; the Prophet <hi>Amos</hi> puts the question, <hi>Can two walke together except they are agreed?</hi> The Apostle exhorteth 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.10. <hi>Now I beseech you brethren by the name of our Lord Jesus Christ, that yee all speak the same thing, and that there be no divisions or schismes among you, but that yee be perfectly joyned together in the same mind, and in the same judgement.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus you see it is a duty to be laboured after, not to be preach'd and writ against, as Mr. <hi>Dell</hi> and others have done, and by oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing the way to it, fly and avoid the society and familiarity with such men, serve not the bad designes of evill men, neither make, (nor side with) factions or parties: be not tossed with every wind of Doctrine. Delight not in novelties, have not mens persons in admiration; be a true Englishman, and prise lawfull liberty, the safety and publike weale of the Kingdom above lust or life, or any thing, which you may well be and do; and yet not cry down our faithfull Brethren of <hi>Scotland,</hi> but carefully maintaine that cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>respondence and covenanted amity with them; which instead of being an obloquie, will set a lustre upon every true Englishman. Pursue with all earnestnesse, a blessed peace; be a friend to all good government.</p>
            <p>Affect not the shadow more then the substance; be zealous for God, lament and grieve for the multitude of Blasphemies and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther great dishonours, which (now more then ever) are daily ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and practized against his Divine Majesty.</p>
            <p>Be true to your Covenant, and tremble at the thought of all such sonnes of wickednesse as dare presume to speak or write any thing against it. with the same care and zeale avoid all novell and spurious interpretations thereof, being urged of purpose, as the most likely and ready way to destroy the obliging nature of it.
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:113763:14"/>Abhor the cursed Toleration, as being hatefull to god and all good men, and destructive to Church and State.</p>
            <p>Yet, as I never did, so I hope never shall oppose or dislike, <hi>that all due care be taken that we persecute not piety and peaceable men, who cannot through scruple of conscience come up in all things to the common rule: But that they may have such a forbearance as may be according to the word of God, may consist with the Covenant, and not be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>structive to the rule it self, nor to the peace of the Church and Kingdom.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And I do seriously professe that my pen hath no quarrell with any, but such as are in opinion or practice wilfull enemies to the said qualifications; and do lament the condition of all such ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nest well-meaning persons; who, by the artifice and cunning of Sectaries are dangerously missed and ensnared.</p>
            <p>It hath been, and is the opinion of many, that we should (instead of answer) slight and scorn those odious libells published against this famous and faithfull City, which hath been the cause they have so long past uncontrol'd, and so seldome answered; but now discerning their presumption to grow so very high, I cannot but declare these my observations touching the sin and misery of these Mountebancks in Religion. And which will prove the ruine of the Kingdoms, if not timely prevented. I have insisted long up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on this unpleasing theame, but with much greif of heart, that such crimes may so justly be charged upon any pretenders to piety.</p>
            <p>If I should enlarge upon matter of fact referable to the prece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent heads, it would appear much more sad; only I should then be tedious, and it would be but raking into a most odious dunghill; I shall therefore forbear, and refer you to the books of that subject which are published to the world in print.</p>
            <p>Reader, you either do, or may see, how pernicious the practises of the Sectaries are, how dangerous it is to be deceived by them, <hi>Ephes.</hi> 6.14. <hi>Stand therefore, having your loyns guirt about with truth, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.21. to the 27. verse. <hi>And having a high-Preist over the house of God, Let us draw near with a true heart, in full assurance of faith, having our hearts sprinkled from an evill conscience, and our bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies washed with pure water.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="26" facs="tcp:113763:15"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Let us hold fast the profession of our faith without wavering (for be is faithfull that promised) And let me consider one another to provoke to love and to good works.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Not forsaking the assembling of our selves together as the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of some is: but exhorting one another, and so much the more, as yee see the day approaching; for if wee sinne wilfully, after that wee have received the knowledge of the truth, there remaines no more sacrifice for sinnes, but a certaine looking for of judgements and fiery indignation, which shall devoure the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>versaries.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>